A war has been going on for billions of years
数十億年も続いている戦争があり
that breeds well armed monsters, who struggle with other monsters for survival.
武装した怪物たちを生み
生存をかけて戦わせている
Having no particular interest in us, most of them are relatively harmless,
人類に特段の関心はなく
ほとんどは比較的無害だ
as our immune systems deal with their weapons easily.
免疫系が彼らの武器を
簡単に処理できる
But there are exceptions.
だが、例外もある
Naegleria fowleri is an amoeba that has not only developed a deadly taste for human brains but is also a match for our defences
Naegleria fowleriというアメーバは
人間の脳を食べて死に至らせ、免疫系にも対応する
and stars in dramatic headlines.
劇的な見出しを飾るスターだ
What happens when this monster enters your body?
この怪物が体内に侵入したら
何がおきるのか？
Naegleria fowleri is an amoeba,
Naegleria fowleriはアメーバだ
a microbe with a nucleus, one of the smallest lifeforms on earth.
核を持つ微生物であり
地球上で最小の生物の一つだ
It is a voracious hunter of bacteria and other critters that it devours whole and rips into pieces.
アメーバは、細菌や他の生物を丸のみして細断する
獰猛なハンターだ
Like many amoebea it is able to transform into different stages that help it survive,
他のアメーバと同様、Naegleria fowleriは
生存のために変形できる
but most of the time Naegleria fowleri is in its trophozoite stage,
ほとんどの場合、Naegleria fowleriは栄養体で
during which it looks like a squishy blob with tiny arms
小さな腕を持つグニャグニャの塊で
and hunts, divides and thrives.
それが狩り、分裂し、繁栄している
Its natural home is in fresh water: ponds, rivers, lakes and hot springs.
本来の生息場所は淡水で
池、川、湖、温水などだが
But unfortunately it also feels happy in pipes, swimming pools, fountains or spas
残念ながら、居心地のいい場所には
パイプ、プール、噴水、温泉などもある
when they are not properly treated.
適切な処置が無い場合だ
The warmer the water, the more it thrives and multiplies.
水温が高いほど
盛んに繁殖していく
So in the summer, when humans seek to cool off and enjoy themselves,
だから、人間が涼しさと楽しさを求める夏は
the chances are highest that both species will interact.
アメーバと遭遇する可能性が
最大になるのだ
Because this makes it hard to avoid,
だから回避は難しく
millions of people regularly have contact with the amoeba, especially in warmer climates,
特に温暖な地域では数百万人が
定期的に接触しており
and many people even seem to have antibodies against it.
その多くが抗体すら持たないようだ
And this is mostly ok, you can even swallow it without consequences.
まあ概ね問題はなく
水を飲んでさえ感染回避は可能だ
Things turn bad when people dive or swim in water contaminated with the amoeba and water splashes high up into their noses.
アメーバに汚染された水を泳いだり潜ったりして
水が鼻の高さまでくると、事態は悪化する
In a single drop of lake water there are millions of viruses, bacteria and amoebea
湖の水一滴には何百万という
ウイルス、細菌、アメーバがいるが
and that isn’t really a big deal.
大した問題ではない
But Naegleria fowleri is different.
だがNaegleria fowleriは違う
Let us zoom into the nose of an unsuspecting victim enjoying a great summer day and see what happens.
夏の一日を楽しむ無防備な犠牲者の鼻を拡大し
何が起きるか見てみよう
First of all, the amoeba doesn’t really want to be inside your nose
第一に、アメーバは望んで
あなたの鼻に入ったのではない
as it is not really looking for trouble, it just wants to eat a few bacteria.
細菌を少し食べたいだけで
トラブルは求めていないのに
Instead it is greeted by your natural defenses.
あなたの免疫系に出迎えられる
Unfortunately for humans, Naegleria fowleri happens to be exceptionally good at generally flying under the radar of your immune system.
困ったことに、Naegleria fowleriはなぜか
免疫系のレーダーを潜り抜けるのが非常にうまい
For example, the inside of your nose is covered by mucosa,
例えば鼻の内側は
粘膜に覆われ
a slime filled with chemicals that kill or stun possible invaders or alert immune cells.
含まれる化学物質は侵入者を殺すか気絶させ
免疫細胞へ警告する
But Naegleria fowleri is not particularly bothered by them
だがNaegleria fowleriは特に困らない
and instead calmly checks out the scenery, mildly annoyed about the whole ordeal.
落ち着いて景色を眺めつつ
この試練に少しイラつく程度だ
Now, if you are unlucky,
もしあなたが不運なら
この微生物は
興味をかきたてるものに出会う
: Nerve cells.
神経細胞だ
Your nose is filled with a large network of olfactory nerve cells
鼻は嗅覚神経細胞の
巨大ネットワークで満ち
that pick up molecules from the outside and transmit their information to your olfactory bulb, the center of smell in your brain.
外界の分子を拾い、その情報を
脳内の嗅覚中枢である嗅球に伝える
To do their job these cells talk to each other by releasing various messenger chemicals
神経細胞は任務遂行のために
様々な伝達物質を出し
and recognizing them via specific receptors.
特定の受容体で認識して交流する
One of the most important of these chemicals is acetylcholine.
特に重要な伝達物質が
アセチルコリンだ
Through sheer evolutionary bad luck,
進化上の不運により
Naegleria fowleri happens to have receptors that recognize acetylcholine.
Naegleria fowleri は偶然にも
アセチルコリン受容体を持っており
And it seems to attract them irresistibly, a little like moths that are attracted by light.
その伝達物質に強く惹きつけられる
光に蛾が集まるように
So as your olfactory nerve cells do their job, using plenty of acetylcholine to talk to the brain,
嗅覚神経細胞が働くとき
脳への伝達に多量のアセチルコリンが使われ
Naegleria fowleri enters your tissue.
Naegleria fowleriが
組織に侵入するのだ
It seems to follow the chemical signals upstream.
伝達物質の上昇流を追うように
Neutrophils, crazy suicide warriors begin to attack the amoebae.
狂気の特攻隊員である好中球が
攻撃を始める
Individually they have no chance against them
一対一では勝ち目はない
as the invaders are large and pretty buff fighters, used to dealing with tough enemies.
アメーバは大型の戦士で
強敵との戦いに馴れているので
（★buffは「研磨」から「手慣れた、熟練の」と解釈しました。そうすると後段と意味が重複するので、結局スルーしています）
So the defenders swarm the intruders and kill them either by vomiting chemicals that punch holes into them
好中球はアメーバに群がり
身体に穴をあける化学物質を吐いたり
or by literally ripping parts of them off and devouring them.
身体の一部を切り取って
食い荒らしたりして殺す
But the Naegleria fowleri train is still on track  and while the Neutrophil attacks slow them down,
だが、好中球の攻撃で遅れても
アメーバは軌道に乗っており
they continue to follow the olfactory nerves to their final destination:
嗅覚神経に沿って
目的地に向かい続ける
Your brain.
あなたの脳だ
This process can take between one and nine days and you’ll probably not notice anything during that time.
このプロセスには1～9日かかり
その間はたぶん、何も気づかない
Until the amoebae reach the olfactory bulb, the center of smell and entrance to your brain.
嗅覚の中枢であり、脳の入り口である嗅球に
たどり着くまでの間だ
Your brain cells are nothing more than helpless victims
あなたの脳は無力な犠牲者であり
and they all release that wonderful acetylcholine.
魅力的なアセチルコリンを
わざわざ放出している
Naegleria fowleri initiates a massacre and releases an onslaught of various attack molecules.
Naegleria fowleriは大虐殺を始め
様々な攻撃分子を猛烈に放出する
Some of them are basically little bombs that rip holes into your cells on contact so their pieces can be eagerly consumed.
分子の一部は、接触した細胞に穴を空ける小型爆弾で
破片にむしゃぶりつける
But Naegleria fowleri is now multiplying - and it's also becoming really creepy.
ここで、このアメーバは増殖を始め
いよいよバケモノじみていく
In a feeding frenzy it can develop up to a dozen suckers called food cups, that look like giant eerie mouths.
食欲が暴走し、フードカップが1ダースも作られる
巨大で不気味な、口のような吸盤だ
The amoebae engage your brain cells, suck them in and rip large “bites” out of them while they are still alive.
アメーバはあなたの生きた脳にとりつき
吸い込み、嚙みちぎっていく
Now things escalate quickly and the disease that will kill you sets in.
事態は急速にエスカレートし
死に至る病が発祥する
Alerted by the massacre, millions of immune cells, Neutrophils, Eosinophils and microglias invade the infected tissue.
大虐殺を受け、好中球、好酸球、ミクログリアが
何百万と感染組織に侵入する
Which is a problem: your immune system is dangerous and not exactly a careful fighter.
問題は、免疫系は本来危険なもので
慎重には戦わないことだ
It's like burning down a forest to kill the wolves inside it
森の中の狼を殺すのに
森を焼き払うようなもので
A really bad idea in the brain.
脳においては最悪の発想だ
They waste no time and attack the amoeba, using all the weapons available to them, from chemicals to trying to eat them alive.
ただちに免疫系は攻撃を始める
化学兵器から直接の捕食まで、あらゆる手段でだ
Neutrophils explode themselves to erect barriers spiked with deadly chemicals.
好中球は自爆し
致死的な化学兵器を含むバリアを張る
A fierce battle ensues.
壮絶な戦闘だ
Naegleria fowleri can actually fight back, itself attacking and killing many immune cells.
Naegleria fowleriも反撃でき
多くの免疫細胞を攻撃し死滅させる
The immune system now throws everything it has at the invader but in vain.
免疫系は全てを侵略者にぶつけるが
無駄に終わる
The complement system, tiny protein bombs that can kill intruders on their own, are easily disabled.
侵入者を殺せる小さなタンパク爆弾
「補体系」も容易に無効化される
★1行目が補体系の説明であるというのが何か伝わりづらい気がして、カギカッコをつけました。
Antibodies, usually one of your superweapons, are just destroyed or swallowed.
超兵器のはずの抗体も
ただ壊されるか飲み込まれる
A high fever that usually slows enemies down does nothing,
侵入者を鈍らせる高熱も無意味だ
as the amoeba actually thrives in the heat.
高温で繁栄しているのだから
All the while the amoebae continue to multiply, fight and devour your brain cells.
その間もアメーバは増殖し、戦い続け
あなたの脳に齧り付いていく
A disastrous chain reaction is taking place.
悲惨な連鎖反応が生じる
One major thing your immune cells do when they fight is to cause inflammation.
戦闘モードの免疫細胞は
炎症を生じさせる
Which directs large amounts of fluid from your bloodstream into the site of an infection.
その結果、血管から大量の体液が
感染部位に流れ込む
So as the battle rages on without a clear winner, more and more fluid enters the brain.
決着が遅れるほど
さらに体液が脳に流れ込んでいくのだ
At this point the human will feel symptoms that quickly escalate.
ここで人間は
症状の急激な加速を感じる
It all begins pretty vaguely, a headache, fever, nausea and vomiting.
まずは漠然とした症状の
頭痛、発熱、吐き気、嘔吐から始まり
As the battle spreads rapidly through the brain serious symptoms appear,
脳内の戦闘が激化すると
症状も深刻化する
from confusion, inability to concentrate to fatigue, seizures and hallucinations.
混乱、集中力の欠如、疲労、発作、幻覚などだ
The brain swells up massively but can’t expand due to the bones surrounding it.
脳は強く膨張するが
頭蓋に囲まれ広がれないため
So it compresses and disables the brainstem that controls things like breathing.
呼吸などを制御する脳幹が
圧迫され機能しなくなる
Usually within a week the patient dies.
通常、1週間以内に
患者は死亡する
Up to 97% of patients infected by the amoeba share this fate.
このアメーバの感染者の97％が
同じ運命をたどる
In almost all cases, by the time an infection by Naegleria fowleri is recognized
ほぼ全てのケースで
感染に気付くころには
the disastrous battle for the brain is already so far along that there is almost nothing to be done.
すでに脳内は苛烈な戦闘中で
手遅れなことがほとんどだ
Not only do we currently not have effective treatments,
有効な治療法が無いばかりか
there are also an abundance of open questions
未解決の謎が山積している
about how an amoeba that usually enjoys its life in open water, is able to overcome our immune system so effectively.
淡水で生活するアメーバが
人間の免疫系に見事に対処できる理由についてだ
So how worried do you need to be about this horrifying killer amoeba?
では、この恐るべき殺人アメーバを
どれだけ警戒すべきか！？
Well, not very.
まあ、そんなに
While the Naegleria fowleri is clearly extremely deadly and the infection truly horrible,
Naegleria fowleri は明らかに極めて致死的だし
感染は真の恐怖だが
there have only been a few hundred cases in the last few decades.
過去数十年で数百件の報告しかない
You are way more likely to drown in a pool than to get infected.
プールで感染するより
溺れる可能性の方が高い
Not only does the amoeba need to be flushed high up your nose,
鼻の深くに付着するだけでなく
it also needs to get a good grip and it also has to make its way through the first lines of your defences.
しっかり掴まり
防御の第一線を通過する必要もある
Ultimately Naegleria fowleri is neither evil nor a huge public health risk.
結局、Naegleria fowleriは
悪魔でも公衆衛生上の巨大リスクでもない
But every year some unlucky people have to deal with it.
ただ毎年、不幸な人々が
相手をさせられている
We still have so much to learn about it
解明すべき点は多く
and until we find a way to treat it,
治療法を見つけるまでは
Naegleria fowleri will continue to be this vague and horrifying thing, hunting in puddles and lakes and sometimes pools.
Naegleria fowleri は水たまりや池、
たまにプールにいる脅威の怪物のままだ
Usually for bacteria. And very occasionally, for people.
基本的には細菌への脅威だが
極めて稀に、人間に牙をむくのだ
- Oh hey, who are you?
「あれ、あなたは誰？」
It is me, your existential dread!
「俺だよ、お前の実存的恐怖だよ」
- Uhm, ok.
「ふーん、そう」
I'm here to make you question your own existence and everything you hold dear in life!
「お前の実存や、大切なもの全てに
疑念を抱かせてやろう」
- Could you not please.
「やめておくれ」
Tooooooo late,
「手遅れだ！」
just look at all these amazing posters FULL of humbling visualisations like the scale of the universe.
「この素晴らしい視覚化ポスターの数々を見ろ
宇宙スケールのやつなんて屈辱的だ」
LOOK! How huge it is and how small you are!
「見ろ、宇宙がいかに大きく
お前がどれだけ小さいかを！」
Look at the education edition, how it dives deep into the history of evolution or all these other scientific fields
「学習用のシリーズも見ろ！進化の歴史など
科学の諸領域に深く潜っている！」
to make you feel bad for all the stuff you don't know!
「自分の無知さにウンザリさせてくれるぞ」
Or look at this one, IT GLOWS IN THE DARK!
「これを見ろ！暗闇で光るんだぞ！」
- But Dread, these do make me feel good actually!
「でもね、僕はグッズが心地いいよ」
They do fill me with excitement and awe about how amazing our universe is
「宇宙の素晴らしさに
興奮と畏敬の念で満たされるし」
and I love learning! And look how pretty they are!
「それに学ぶのが好きだし！グッズは可愛いし！」
Nooooooooo, I can't persist in the presence of awe.
「ああああ！畏敬の念を抱かれたら敵わん！」
Graglgrglglg.
「グワー」
If you too want to overcome your existential dread, make your life beautiful and also support Kurzgesagt
あなたも実存的恐怖を克服し、人生を美しくし
そしてKurzgesagtを応援し
so we can put thousands of hours into our videos and release them for free,
数千時間かけた動画の
無料公開を支えたいなら
you can get these and many many more amazing posters or shirts or so many more things in our shop.
紹介した品や、素晴らしいポスターやシャツなどが
公式ショップに多数あります
We put as much care into our products as into our videos,
動画と同じだけ
製品に愛を注いでおり
trying to find something clever or a new angle that will challenge your perspective while still teaching you the core aspects.
上手い方法や新たな切り口を見出し
本質を伝えながら視野を広げようとしています
It’s the best way to support what we do on this channel.
ショップのご利用は
このチャンネルの活動を支援する最良の方法です